Finding Aid for Roger Warren Barney and Jane Lockwood Barney papers, 1929-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Roger Warren Barney and Jane Lockwood Barney papers 1929-2002
Barney, Roger Warren.
2008125 Aa 2
Roger Barney was an Episcopal priest serving first in New Hampshire, later as a Navy chaplain during World War II, with Parishfield Community in Brighton, Michigan, and as associate rector of St. Andrew’s Episcopal Church in Ann Arbor. Jane Lockwood Barney worked with the Institute of Gerontology and as advocate on behalf of the elderly. The collection includes personal correspondence, sermons, and subject files relating to their education, his service during World War II, and their ministry at Parishfield.
11 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated to the library by Jane Lockwood Barney (donor no. 10050 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Roger Warren Barney was born on June 11, 1916 in Boston, Massachusetts. He grew up in the nearby community of Dorchester where he attended the Gilbert Stuart School and later Boston English High School. After graduating high school, Barney attended Dartmouth College where he was introduced to the Episcopal Church through the ministry of Father Leslie Hodder. He was eventually confirmed, and along with other students, served small churches in the area. Barney graduated Dartmouth in 1937, and continued his studies at Union Theological Seminary, where he made the acquaintance of Jane Lockwood, of Buchanan, Virginia.
After graduating from Union Theological Seminary with a master of divinity degree in 1940, Barney was ordained to the Episcopal Ministry as a deacon in Trinity Church, New York City in 1940, and later as a priest by Bishop John Dallas at St. John the Baptist Church in Sanbornville in 1941. In June of 1941, Barney was wed to Ms. Lockwood, and the two moved to New Hampshire, where Barney served at Christ Church in North Conway, and Saint Andrew's in the Valley in Tamworth.
In 1943, Barney joined the United States Navy as a chaplain. For a time, he was stationed at Parris Island, South Carolina, and eventually saw action in the Pacific Theatre, including the battle of Iwo Jima.
After the war, Barney returned to New Hampshire, where he became rector of St. Mark's, Ashland and director of the Mountain Mission by Mail, a program that served children in remote areas with weekly mailings, radio programs, and personal visits. In 1950, Barney was asked to become Archdeacon and Executive Secretary of the Episcopal Diocese of New Hampshire, and the Barneys moved to Concord with their then young children, Alice, James, Jonathan, and Daniel. In the summer of 1955, while vacationing at MacMahan Island, Barney contracted polio. He spent the next 14 months in treatment at Mary Hitchcock hospital in Hanover.
In 1957, after being released from the hospital, Barney and his family moved to Brighton, Michigan, where he served on the staff of the Parishfield Community with colleagues Francis Ayres, and Jim Guinan. The Parishfield community was a semi-independent agency of the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan established to create a ministry of lay people who would further the mission of the church in society. The community hoped to renew the church through an awareness of society's critical issues, focusing on topics such as religion, industry, corrections, freedom, and poverty. At the disbanding of the Parishfield community in 1967, Barney became Associate Rector for Administration of St. Andrew's Church in Ann Arbor, a post he held until his death in 1978.
Barney was survived by his four children, and his wife Jane, who, for many years preceding and following Barney's death, worked with the University of Michigan's Institute of Gerontology. Mrs. Barney was very active in working with senior centers and advocating senior citizens' issues.
Roger Barney's papers date from his youth in the late 1920s up to his death in 1978, and document his personal interests and activities, his education, his time in the armed forces during World War II, and his professional life as an Episcopal minister. Likewise, the papers of Jane Barney date from the 1930s to the early 2000s, and document her education, her family life, and her work with the University of Michigan's Institute of Gerontology and other organizations concerned with senior citizens. The collection is comprised of the following series: Roger Warren Barney Files, Jane Lockwood Barney Files, and Correspondence.
Subjects:
Barney, Jane Lockwood.; Barney, Roger Warren.; Clergy--Michigan.; Episcopal Church--Michigan.; Institute of Gerontology (University of Michigan-Wayne State University); Iwo Jima, Battle of, Japan, 1945.; Military chaplans--United States.; Parishfield.; Poliomyelitis--Patients--New Hampshire.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Barney, Roger Warren.; Dartmouth College.; Iwo Jima, Battle of, Japan, 1945.; Parishfield.
Contributors:
Barney, Jane Lockwood.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sermons.
- Roger Warren Barney Files 1929-1978
  Roger Warren Barney Files (1929-1978, 5.5 linear feet) document Barney's childhood, his education, his time as a chaplain in the armed forces, his career in New Hampshire and Michigan, and his personal interests and projects.
  - Personal Files 1930s-1960s
    - A-K, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - L-Z and Miscellaneous, 15 folders (Box 2)
  - Bills and Finances 1937-1968 (Box 3)
  - Assorted Church Handouts 1929-1967 (Box 3)
  - Radical Theology 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - New Culture 1965-1967 (Box 3)
  - Christian Organizations 1941 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1940-1983 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Documents (Box 3)
  - Address Book (Box 3)
  - RWB Youth
    - Boy Scout Newsletters 1930-1931 (Box 3)
    - Horses and Camp Documents 1931-1935 (Box 3)
    - Journals 1935 (Box 3)
  - Education
    - Gilbert Stuart School 1928-1929 (Box 3)
    - English High School 1929-1961 (Box 3)
    - Dartmouth 1935-1937 (Box 3)
    - Union Theological Seminary 1938-1940, 2 folders (Box 3)
      (term papers and thesis)
    - Ordination 1940-1941 (Box 3)
  - Marriage 1941 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Maps (Box 3)
  - Navy service, World War II
    - Iwo Jima Diary 1945-1956 (Box 3)
    - Discharge Notice 1946 (Box 3)
    - WW II Souvenirs 1943-1946, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Group Photographs (Box 4)
    - Iwo Jima Chapel Photographs (Box 4)
    - Notebooks (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook (Folder 1)
      (located at Ac)
  - New Hampshire Churchman 1951-1955 (Box 4)
  - Mary Hitchcock Hospital 1955-1956 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence to RWB in Hospital 1955-1956 (Box 4)
  - Fundraising Controversy 1957 (Box 4)
  - Wendell Barney 1962-1963 (Box 4)
  - Parishfield
    - Staff Meetings 1963-1964 (Box 4)
    - Newsletters 1956-1967 (Box 4)
    - Library 1962-1963 (Box 4)
    - Tennis Courts 1964-1965 (Box 4)
    - Otto and Janet Hopp 1959-1961 (Box 4)
    - Detroit Industrial Association 1959-1962 (Box 4)
    - Industrial Courses in Practical Politics 1961 (Box 4)
    - Action and Service 1966 (Box 4)
    - Alinsky/Carmichael Conference 1967 (Box 4)
    - City Seminar on Unintended Racism 1968 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Photographs (Box 4)
  - St. Andrews, Ann Arbor 1972 (Box 4)
  - Death (Letters of Condolence, Obituaries, etc.) 1978 (Box 4)
  - Assorted Photographs and Negatives (Box 4)
  - Bulletins 1956-1978, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Sermons
    - 1940-1970, 28 folders (Box 5)
    - 1971-1978 and Miscellaneous, 9 folders (Box 6)
- Jane Lockwood Barney Files 1933-2002
  Jane Lockwood Barney Files (1933-2002, 1 linear foot) consist of various school papers and records, documents relating to the Parishfield community, records of Mrs. Barney's work with the University of Michigan's Institute of Gerontology, various reports and papers written by Mrs. Barney or relating to her work, and assorted papers from the Barney children.
  - Personal Files
    - A-Z and Miscellaneous, 10 folders (Box 6)
  - School Papers 1933-1970, Undated, 12 folders (Box 6)
  - Parishfield
    - Book 1945-2002 (Box 7)
    - Mimi Ayres 2002 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - University of Michigan employment information 1971 (Box 7)
  - University of Michigan Institute of Gerontology reports 1973-1981, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Images of Old Age in America 1978 (Box 7)
  - Child Development Center 1957 (Box 7)
  - Women's Liberation 1969-1973 (Box 7)
  - Profile of the Elderly Population of Inner-City Detroit 1969 (Box 7)
  - The Ferndale Wall 1969 (Box 7)
  - Community Care Center 1970 (Box 7)
  - Assorted reports 1974-1988 (Box 7)
  - Nursing Home Community Council 1980 (Box 7)
  - A Legend of Virginia (Box 7)
  - Pamphlets 1967-1968 (Box 7)
  - Newsletters 1983-1985 (Box 7)
  - Newspapers and Clippings 1993 (Box 7)
  - Senate Resolution No. 610 1986 (Box 7)
  - Barney Children
    - Parishfield News 1959-1961, 3 folders (Box 7)
- Correspondence 1930s-1970s
  Correspondence (1930s-1970s, 4.5 linear feet) is comprised of personal letters between Roger and Jane Barney, their children, their parents, their friends, and their work colleagues.
  - Roger Warren Barney Correspondence with
    - Jane Lockwood Barney
      - 1939-1940, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - 1941-1956, 10 folders (Box 8)
    - Mr. And Mrs. Rhodes Lockwood 1940-1954 (Box 8)
    - Father 1942-1943 (Box 8)
    - Moving Away 1957 (Box 8)
    - Parishfield
      - Joseph A Pelham 1966-1972 (Box 8)
      - Hugh White 1963-1971 (Box 8)
      - Francis Ayres 1956-1961 (Box 8)
      - James B. Guinan 1966-1973 (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Rusty Miller 1957-1960 (Box 9)
    - Jock and Emily Brown 1957-1961 (Box 9)
    - Margo Brown 1957-1961 (Box 9)
    - John Dallas 1942-1960 (Box 9)
    - Robert Dunn 1952-1954 (Box 9)
    - Leslie Hodder 1940-1964 (Box 9)
    - Richard 1938-1939 (Box 9)
    - Dymoke 1941-1961 (Box 9)
    - Letters of Condolence 1978 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Jane Lockwood Barney Correspondence with
    - Roger Warren Barney 1939-1940, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Roger Warren Barney 1941-1956 and Bound Edition, 8 folders (Box 10)
    - Mother 1935-1954, Undated, 15 folders (Box 10)
    - Father 1934-1940 (Box 10)
    - Anne Lockwood
      - 1943-1948, 6 folders (Box 10)
      - 1949-1970 and Miscellaneous, 23 folders (Box 11)
    - Anne Lockwood Correspondence (Box 11)
    - Peggy 1941-1951 (Box 11)
    - Marjorie T Gregg 1957-1961 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
    - Barney Children Correspondence (Box 11)